<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The camp of Christ, and the camp of Antichrist, all troopers after the Lambe. Revel. 10. 11. 14. or his two horns, Rev. 13. 11, 12.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79562</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C398</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E127_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21625</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871464</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871464</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156202</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79562)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156202)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 22:E127[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The camp of Christ, and the camp of Antichrist, all troopers after the Lambe. Revel. 10. 11. 14. or his two horns, Rev. 13. 11, 12.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 16 1642".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation --  Criticism, interpretation, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:156202:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE CAMP OF CHRIST, AND THE CAMP OF ANTICHRIST, all Troopers after the LAMBE. <hi>Revel.</hi> 10.11.14. or his two Horns, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.11, 12.</head>
            <argument>
               <p n="1">1. The Troopers for Chriſt are diſtinguiſhed from the Troopers of Antichrist, by the end they ayme, and the ſide they undertake; for the one muſt be against Chriſt, that's diſcuſſed and reſolved: the other are encouraged for Chriſt, by the certainty of the victory in the end, proved all at large out of Scripture, but eſpecially out of the Apocalips.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here is likewiſe declared how the government of this Kingdom hath been ſince it had first a being till now.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Generall, the Camp of Christ, called, choſen, faithfull in fight with Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt and his Army.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Declared to be fought under foure Standards, reduced to foure Enſignes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared at large what they be: The Lambes Camp compared to a Lion for cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and valour; to a Man for wiſdom; to an Ox for patience and induſtrie; to an Eagle for ſpeed and expedition: Antichriſt is the Generall of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates Armie.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Two Captains, two Camps, their fatall and finall warres, an inſtance in our Kingdom, <hi>Revel. 17.14.</hi> They ſhall make warre with the Lambe, ſhewing the age of Antichriſts it being, and her now Ruine.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Warre proved lawfull from Scripture and Reaſon, from the breach of Law and its own duty to hinder the Kings coming to rule by Arbitrary and Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, as for <hi>Hezekiah</hi> to oppoſe <hi>Senacheribs</hi> coming against Iſrael.</p>
            </argument>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Wicked men take no notice of that which good men obſerve, <hi>viz.</hi> the time, times, and half a time of Antichriſt. <bibl>Dan. 12.7.10.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe Warre is wonderfull that Antichriſt ſhould fight againſt the Lambe with his own Horns; for what are the horns of the Lambe but his own power? And what is that power, but the power of the keyes? And what power have the keyes, but to bind and looſe, remit and retain ſinnes? And to whom is this power given, but to the Paſtors of the Church? And of them who
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156202:2"/>
challenge the ordination of all Miniſters, and the juriſdiction over all perſons, but the Biſhops? And therefore of them we conclude, what they would have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to revelation. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 13.11. the ſecond Beaſt had two horns like the Lambe, the honour of Epiſcopacie, but he ſpake as a Dragon, the dread of their calling, and diſgrace of ſo great a dignitie. The <hi>ten horns,</hi> Dan 7.24. Rev. 17 12. are expounded to our hands to be <hi>ten Kings,</hi> that take away the <hi>Ceſars,</hi> 2. Theſ. 2.6, 7. and ſucceed him in his kingdom, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.1. the crowns were upon the ſixth head, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12 3 that is one <hi>Ceſar</hi> held them, and by civill and barbarous warres ten enjoy them to themſelves, which is called an Apoſtaſie from <hi>Ceſar,</hi> 2. Theſ. 2.3 and this is firſt in order, but in time we muſt joyn it with another from Chriſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.12. and this is to Antichriſt, to whom the other give their power, and both fight with the Lambe and his choſen Army, who as Troopers in white, and upon white horſes, make their expedition againſt a cruell companie with the greateſt innocencie and alacritie in the world. Antichriſt is ſaid to come out of the <hi>earth, Revel.</hi> 13 11. both for ſecreſie and ſilence. He is not ſeen ſo ſoon as the ten Horns that riſe out of the <hi>Sea,</hi> for they are up in commotion, but he ſteals up in their troubled waters, and at their back ſubdues them, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25. Let my counſell be acceptable to the King and Kingdom, and conſider our Camps, and how we have argued our ſelves into a civill warre, and from words are come to blows. Both cannot be innocent, or Caviiiers of the ſame condition. The Troo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers in white muſt be known by the truth, and the truth by God and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. God, if we defend true Religion; and the Countrey, if we ſeek the peace of it.</p>
            <p>The miſerie of our warre ſhall be the meditation of our miſerie, ever ſince we were a Kingdom. We have been ruled by <hi>Romanes</hi> from the firſt King that ever we had, who having killed his own Father by accident, exiled himſelf into this Iſland. A thouſand yeers and more before Chriſt, <hi>Brute</hi> a noble Romane ruled us, and ſome 58. yeers before Chriſt we fell into a civill warre, and <hi>Julius Ceſar</hi> conquered us, and when the <hi>Ceſars</hi> were conquered, we fell into a civill warre, and the <hi>Saxons Fortiger</hi> ſent for to help him conquered his ſonne <hi>Vortimer,</hi> and themſelves by a civill warre fell into an <hi>Heptarchie,</hi> and in this time came the Monke from the Pope and maſtered our Biſhops, and by them our Kings, and at this time they are ſuſpected to joyn with a Malignant Partie, to part the King and his Councell, and all becauſe he cannot have a Monarchie of their making, which is ſtamped with that character, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8 9 11. where the judgement, reaſon, or will of the King is tyrannie, if the judgement of the Kingdom be not in it. Nineteen Propoſitions propounded by his Councell have provoked him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, and made many to think his very Councell would impoſe a tyrannie upon him, and all this for want of a true diſtinction between juſtice diſtributive, and commutative. Diſtributive of honours to deſerving perſons, and in this the Kings Prerogative cannot be violated. Privy Counſellors, Biſhops, Judges, Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, publick Officers, Courtiers, Servants to the King are by him to be honored,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156202:2"/>
but not to the hurt of the Kingdom. His Majeſtie muſt look by diſtributive j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtice to the qualities of the perſons he honours, that they be as himſelf, not for themſelves, but the common good. Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> would ſay, <hi>Populus nihi preciociſſimus,</hi> Courtiers, <hi>Maledictus,</hi> and when his Majeſtie ſaies his beloved peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, too many curſe them, and ſay keep them under. By reaſon of the which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion they cry to God, and we hope God will heare them, as he hath in this Parliament; which zealouſly ſeek the peoples good, not to diſtribute honours the right of the King, but prevent their hurt the right of the Kingdom by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutative juſtice, that reſpects not perſons but things; and if his Majeſtie meane to diſtribute hurtfull honours, his Councell may well requeſt that commutative juſtice may not be exchanged into tyrannie. <hi>Jus militiae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m bellum indicendi quam gerendi cum inimicis, pacis quoque contrahendae &amp; paciſcendae cum peregrinis eſt lex Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis.</hi> To proclaim and make warre, to contract and make peace, are in diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive juſtice the Royalties of a King: but in commutative juſtice, the men and money the King would have to make war, muſt come from common conſent. Let this be the carriage of the Common-wealth, and we ſhall ſoon be at peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>The Campe of Chriſt, called, choſen, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, in fight with <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and his Armie.</head>
            <p>THe Campe of Chriſt conſiſts of 144000, and the Campe of Antichriſt of 666; not becauſe Chriſt hath the greater number, but the better men, as being vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins undefiled with women, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4. The other is a round number of a name, of a Beaſt, of a man, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.17, 18. There will be great wiſdome to ſearch them out, and as oppoſites compared together will more clearely ſhew themſelves. The 144000 is diſtributed into 12 Tribes, and the 12 Tribes into foure Beaſts, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.6. and here we muſt begin our ſearch, <hi>Domine, ediſcere nobis parabolam iſtam, Mat.</hi> 15.15. Wee muſt in the alluſion fetch our Campe from the Congregation in the Wilderneſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.10. <hi>Thy Beaſts dwelt therein;</hi> So our <hi>Engliſh</hi> ancient tranſlation hath it, and the originall word is ſo, and our new tranſlation gives us the ſenſe of it, for by the Beaſts we muſt underſtand Gods people, which in this booke of the <hi>Revelation</hi> is the ordinary expreſſion of that part of the Church, as the 24 Elders are of the Paſtours, to whom the 24 thrones belong to judge the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the crownes of gold to ſhew their rule. They are the presbyteries of the Church, from the which our Biſhops are fallen into a temporall juriſdiction, worſe then any other Lay-Elderſhip, under the which for this thouſand yeares our Church hath groaned and if we will learne a true presbytery, we muſt finde it in the firſt 600 yeares. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14 and <hi>Cornelius</hi> and <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> uſe it in the ſame ſenſe, and that without the Elderſhip they did nothing in the Conſiſtorie. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 6.13.35. <hi>Presbyt. &amp; Diacon. Cornel. Cypr. Ep.</hi> 46. doubtleſſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156202:3"/>
the 24 Presbyteries allude to the 24 Ephemeries, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.4. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.8. But there is now no ſpeaking of Conſiſtories, we muſt follow the Camp, as <hi>David</hi> did from <hi>Hebron</hi> to take <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> from the <hi>Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſites,</hi> before wee bring the Arke of God into any peaceable Tabernacle, and wee have fixed our ſelves in the <hi>Lambes Campe</hi> under foure Standards, that expreſſe both the order and excellency of it. The 12 Tribes of old were reduced to foure Enſignes, <hi>Judah, Iſſachar,</hi> and <hi>Zebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> to a <hi>Lyon: Reuben, Simeon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>Gad</hi> to a <hi>Man: Ephraim, Manaſſes</hi> and <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> to an <hi>Oxe</hi> or <hi>Bullocke: Dan, Aſer,</hi> and <hi>Nephtali</hi> to an <hi>Eagle.</hi> Thus were the Tribes quartered, and from them we take the ſpirituall meaning of the Lambes Campe, for <hi>fortitude</hi> and courage in the Lyon: for <hi>wiſdome</hi> and prudence in a man: for <hi>patience</hi> and induſtry in the labouring Oxe: for <hi>ſpeed</hi> and expedition in an Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle; and we may further take notice of the names of Beaſts in this Booke, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe both the Campe of Chriſt, and the Campe of Antichriſt. Beaſts are Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemes for both, yet in Greeke their names are not the ſame. <hi>Zoa</hi> is for Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the word ſignifies <hi>life.</hi> The other is <hi>Therion,</hi> and there be two of that kinde, the Beaſt with <hi>ten hornes,</hi> and the Beaſt with <hi>two:</hi> the firſt makes up Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts Army, as it conſiſts of the people that follow him, and the ſecond is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt himſelf, or the Biſhops that abuſe the power of the Lamb in the two keys, turning them into ſo many hornes to the hurt of the Saints; for if it were not ſo there ſhould be no ſuch cauſe to complaine of them as now is done by all men, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thoſe that are no enemies to their calling. If they had uſed the keyes aright, and not made hornes of them, long might they and their calling have flouriſhed, but now the crownes on their heads, and thrones they have ſitten upon, are like to be ſhaken; and as <hi>Simeon</hi> the propheticall Monke foreſeeing an earth quake, whipped the pillars of the Church, bidding them ſtand faſt, for they ſhould be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; ſo might theſe pillars have foreſeene their ſcourge, if they by whipping of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had not thought their ſtanding had been out of the danger of a Parliament. I would wiſh them to ſtruggle no longer, but to joyne their learning with others, and ſeriouſly obſerve the times, and what miſchiefe they have done by the keyes; which I cannot but honour in the Epiſcopall Dignitie, and doe verily beleeve that in the Presbytery, the <hi>Thrones</hi> and the <hi>Crownes</hi> doe not equally belong to all the Elders. The thing I ſhall note is, that the Lambes hornes make Antichr ſt as well in <hi>England</hi> as at <hi>Rome;</hi> and ſince <hi>Auſten</hi> the Monke medled with us, our Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie hath had too much of divine right, and by the exceſſe of that is like to bring Church Government into a defect, if both extreames be not prevented; but I ſay we muſt have the fire of civill warre quenched, before we can be quickned in the right uſe of the keyes. I have begun the Campe at the foure Standards, reduced the 12 Tribes to them, and now muſt number the Tribes as they are elſewhere no where numbred, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. Each Tribe hath the like number, and that is compleatly twelve thouſand, ſurmounting the Beaſts almoſt one halfe, yet put them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and they are above halfe ſhort of his number, if we compare the great Court of the Temple with the Temple it ſelfe, as the holy Ghoſt hath done, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1, 2.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156202:3"/>
What a number of Gentiles may ſtand in <hi>Atrio magno,</hi> in reſpect of the inwarp Temple, and therefore it we goe on to view both Campes, we ſhall learne out in the end the myſtery. Certainly, in ſix and twelve is ſome hidden ſecret. The great and grand Captaine of our Campe hath his under-Captaines, and they are the 12 Apoſtles, in this booke called 12 Starres, to give the Church light, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1. Secondly, they lie in the foundation with the Prophets, to beare it up for ſinking in the ſand of unſound doctrine, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.14. Every building is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to its foundation, and all companies to their Captaines; and in this Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt ſheweth himſelfe that ſtands ſo much for <hi>Peter,</hi> that he would lay all upon him, becauſe he is called <hi>Petros,</hi> which ſignifies a ſtone, and among 12 fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſtones he is one, and perchance may be the firſt in order, but under none, and therefore they are laid orderly one by one, that the Tribes may build upon them all. So was it firſt, and ſince the 12 Apoſtles have left their cure to 24 Elders to be underſtood by the Ephemeries of the Prieſts and Levites, but I ſuppreſſe my no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and will ſet upon the hurtfull hornes of the Church, that is, Kings and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. Kings and Kingdomes that make the Campe of Antichriſt, and Biſhops that make Antichriſt to be their Generall. I hope Kings that have helped the Whore will hate her, and Biſhops that are good, if any be ſo, for the moſt beleeve there are none, will no more horne it, but hate that office, and learne as brethren to exerciſe the keyes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>Two Captains, two Camps. Their fatall and finall warres. An Inſtance in our Kingdom.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rev. 17.14.</bibl> Theſe ſhall make warre with the Lambe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe <hi>ten hornes</hi> given to the Beaſt with <hi>two horns</hi> ſhall make warres with the <hi>Lambe</hi> and his called, choſen, and faithfull Servants. The ten horns are theſe, <hi>Vortimer</hi> and <hi>Hengiſt</hi> in <hi>England; Childerike, Gunderike,</hi> and <hi>Theodorike</hi> in <hi>France; Riciarius</hi> in <hi>Spaine, Genſerike</hi> in <hi>Africke; Theodemire</hi> in <hi>Panonia; Marcian</hi> in <hi>Greece. Ceſar</hi> hinders the being of the Beaſt, and theſe ten Kings make warre for him, and the Apoſtaſie from him and Chriſt begin <hi>una hora, ver.</hi> 12. It is a rule in the Word that wrath ſhould be feared when God does firſt inflict it, as in the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitie of the City and the Sanctuary, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 25.3.8. There be <hi>ſeven yeers</hi> diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and the judgement begins with the firſt to account the ſeventie yeers cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitie. But in Mercies it is clean contrary, the return of the people was a great bleſſing, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 1.1. but the building of the Sanctuary a greater, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 6.14. and ſo the ſure account of 70. <hi>weeks</hi> for the wellfare of the Jews muſt begin with the ſecond yeer of <hi>Darius Nothus, Ezr.</hi> 4.24. Happy are the Nations that take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of Chriſt when he is angry, leſt it kindle into wrath and they periſh, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156202:4"/>
12. <hi>Bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi> Mercie is at hand to this Nation that with zeal ſeek to ſet up Gods Sanctuary amongſt us, and the time will be ſhortly when we ſhall ſee it, in the expulſion of thoſe clouds that have fallen upon us ſince Reformation began amongſt us; but by reaſon of the <hi>Samaritanes</hi> that dwell amongſt us, could not to this day be accompliſhed. You have heard that judgement ſhould be ſpeedily looked unto, and Antichriſt was not of 700. yeers thought of, but began as <hi>Magnum mundo malum,</hi> when theſe ten Kings fell from one <hi>Ceſar:</hi> They are the Apoſtles words, 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3. <hi>a falling away firſt,</hi> that is, of duty to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and faith to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. The Crowns depart from the heads of the <hi>Ceſars, Revel.</hi> 12.3. to the horns of theſe Kings, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.1. This Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie of kingdoms is the evidence we muſt have for the other being a myſterie, and not ſo manifeſt at the firſt. There are noted three diviſions of the Romane Monarchie, the firſt by <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> the ſecond by <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> the third by <hi>Charles</hi> the great. We muſt begin at the ſecond, for no ſooner had <hi>Honorius</hi> and <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> the Empire ſhared between them, but the Weſt part was quickly diſtracted and dilacerated as we have ſaid, and <hi>Augustus Ceſar</hi> breathed out the ghoſt in <hi>Auguſtulus,</hi> when <hi>Odoacer</hi> made him abdicate and deveſt himſelf of all Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all dignitie. The miſerie began by <hi>Alaricus, Ann.</hi> 395. was followed by <hi>Rada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaiſus,</hi> and the miſeries of warre like a Northerne ſtorme, <hi>Revel.</hi> 7. fell upon the people as graſſe, and the Princes of the Provinces as the taller Cedars, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.2. and then the very mountain of the Monarchie was moved, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.8. and cloven aſunder into ten kingdoms, and the Weſterne ſtarre fals out of the orbe thereof, <hi>Revel.</hi> 8.10. ſo that between the firſt aſſault by <hi>Alaricus</hi> and this of <hi>Odoacer, Ann.</hi> 475. we may ſtate the diviſion to be made perfect in the number of ten Kings, <hi>Anno</hi> 456.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martian</hi> in the Eaſt was a good King in thoſe miſerable times, and had peace, and died before he had fully reigned ſeven yeers, leaving behind him great grief in the hearts of the people, becauſe they loſt ſo good a man. He called the fourth generall Councell, wherein <hi>Leo</hi> and his Legates ſtormed at the honour done to the Patriarke of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> fearing ſome might advance him above the Pope, whoſe perking up in pride prepared for Antichriſt, who prevailed leaſt in the Eaſt till the ſecond <hi>Nicene Councell,</hi> which was the firſt that ever decreed the worſhip of Images. The Greek Emperours ſtill retaining the name, as <hi>Leo Iſaurus, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinus Cabalinus, Nicephorus, Stauratius, Leo A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>menus, Michael Baldus, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus,</hi> oppoſed, when <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſecond, and third, <hi>Paul</hi> the firſt, <hi>Stephen</hi> the fourth, <hi>Adrian</hi> the firſt and ſecond, <hi>Leo</hi> the third, <hi>Nicholas</hi> the firſt, &amp;c. upheld them. 338. Biſhops in a Councell at <hi>Conſtantinople, Ann.</hi> 754 ſolemnly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, and 787 their veneration was made a Law, which to that day was a private opinion, and as <hi>Irene,</hi> and after her <hi>Baſilius</hi> gave Images their firſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſo God diſhonoured their ſucceſſion with the <hi>Saracens</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> and the next Generall Councels, as the Papiſts call them, were all to make warre with the judgements of God for the ſinnes of the Church, and the children of God that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156202:4"/>
but none at all to pull down Idolatrie, for the ten Councels called by the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> are not one of them like the firſt, but are found to handle theſe matters, fitter for a Councell of Warre, then Conſiſtory of Prieſts. Firſt they conſult of an holy Warre with the <hi>Saracens</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> and ſo pilgrimes go out of the Weſt into the Eaſt to purchaſe graves to themſelves in the Holy Land by fighting with God in his two woes, <hi>Revel</hi> 9. and the very ſinne that cauſed them is expreſſed, <hi>v.</hi> 20. of which they repented not, and proſpered accordingly. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, they are recalled again from the Eaſt into the Weſt, to fight with the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> and Emperours that ſtood in the Popes light, and laſtly the Kings and Princes of <hi>Germanie</hi> that have forſaken the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> how are they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted as <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and ſo you have all the Generall Councels held by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and I wonder they do not bluſh at their words, for the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them of horrible pride, and they have denied two of them in ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of Orders as if they had erred in a point of Faith, when they uſed their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full libertie in ſuch things as were moſt indifferent. The fifth Generall Councell condemned <hi>Vigilius</hi> for a curſed <hi>Neſtorian.</hi> The ſixth judged <hi>Honorius</hi> for an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall <hi>Monothlite.</hi> The ſeventh and eighth manifeſt them to be guilty of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie never decreed before by any Councels, but condemned by all, and the ten laſt (the worſt of all) are called by Popes againſt regall, and Imperiall authoritie, and condemne truth for hereſie, Saints for Hereticks, and prove the Pope the greateſt Tyrant in the world. If from <hi>Martian</hi> we caſt our eyes upon the 9. Kings, I know not one of them to be good, and for our Nation before <hi>Vortimer</hi> I can ſay much both for Kings and Biſhops. We had the firſt Chriſtian King and Emperor in the world. <hi>An.</hi> 181. <hi>Lucius</hi> ſent to <hi>Eleutherius</hi> for a Biſhop, Rome being then famous, and his kingdom preſerved pure religion to the daies of <hi>Diocletian,</hi> &amp; in that 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> perſecution we were tried for it. Our nation is thought to receive the Goſpel from the miniſterie of <hi>Joſeph of Aramathea,</hi> which was purely maintained above 250. yeares. It was the onely Sanctuary of the Saints, and for them being perſecuted to flee unto. In the tenth Perſecution <hi>Diacleſian</hi> found us out, as being the moſt generall, cruell, fatall and finall of all the reſt, as we may feare this to be in which wee are, and may be the laſt by Antichriſt, as that was by the Pagans. This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved our faith, and I finde it fayled not till <hi>Auſten</hi> the Monke came from <hi>Rome.</hi> And I pray you note it as being noted in the booke of God. I would faine know ſeeing all the <hi>Seven Seales</hi> have their Indexes, as <hi>foure Beaſts</hi> for the foure firſt, and <hi>earthquake</hi> for the ſixt, and <hi>Seven Trumpets</hi> for the laſt. What is meant by an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar</hi> for the fifth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9. certainely, <hi>Martyrdome,</hi> and of all the ten Perſecutions that is called <hi>Aera Martyrum,</hi> the age of the Martyrs, as being the greateſt an moſt remarkeable, and ended in our Nation, becauſe he that put an end to it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, was the <hi>Great Conſtantine,</hi> borne in our Nation, and for the Church to deliver it. After him we fell into a diviſion and the two Kings I mentioned began our miſery, and of <hi>Britons</hi> wee became <hi>Saxons,</hi> and fell into an <hi>Heptarchie,</hi> and from <hi>Rome</hi> comes <hi>Auſten,</hi> and lands in <hi>Kent,</hi> the firſt part of our ſeven Kingdoms,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156202:5"/>
and there begins as great a confuſion in the Church, as there was in the State. He found many godly men of the Clergie which he inſulted over, and being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken by them as uſed to no Romane pride, or Popiſh orders, but following ſuch as came from the Eaſt, which <hi>Rome</hi> abhorred, they would none of his reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therefore like a limbe of Antichriſt he begins their perſecution, and by ſuch <hi>Romane hornes</hi> made warre with the Lambe, which leſſe or more hath conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to this day; for as the <hi>ten hornes</hi> that have uſurped the Crownes from the <hi>Caeſars,</hi> ſo the <hi>two hornes</hi> that the Biſhops uſurpe from Chriſt are uſed againſt him, and have for 900 yeares, as a booke taken out of the Records of the Tower hath ſhewed unto us, plainly proving the keyes of the Church by the Biſhops to have beene turned into hornes to the hurt of it; for it is they that challenge the <hi>Lambes hornes,</hi> that is, the power of the keyes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.11. to themſelves, and by the Lambes owne hornes fight againſt him, and cauſe the ten hornes ſo to doe, who are rather ſeduced by them, then cruell to Chriſtians, being Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s themſelves; for it were unnaturall for the members of the bodie to doe ſo, except ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, or Divine inſpired with his ſpirit ſhould doe it, and my conjecture is not in vaine by the words of a Pope himſelfe, which are theſe, <hi>Rex ſuperbiae prope eſt, &amp; quod dici nefas eſt, Sacerdotum eſt praeparatus exercitus, Greg. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 38. A King of pride is not the Pope alone, but a prepared Army of Prieſts, and therefore may in our Biſhops extend to us, and yet it is not they as Biſhops, but as they uſe their keyes for hornes, and cauſe Kings to uſe their Crownes ſo, to whom in the Lambe himſelfe, I ſhall now yeeld a better example in their Warres.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Piè regnare, rectè judicare, juſtè pugnare,</hi> to reigne religiouſly, to judge rightly, and righteouſly to make warre, are proclaimed in Heaven by a divine Herald when the Captaine of our Salvation goes out to warre. He ſits upon a white horſe when he gives Crownes to the obedient, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.2. and caſts them downe in the diſobedient, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.18. The Prieſts have Crownes and Thrones, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.4. grant them to be the Biſhops, and as we have ſaid of their two hornes, to be their honours from the Lambe, yet will not the Lambe ſpare them in the great day of his wrath, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6 16, 17. Let Princes and Prelates thinke of their powers and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives as vaine things with an angry Lambe; but why ſay I angry, when he calls to a nuptiall Supper, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.7.9 O but it is the Supper of the great God, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. and the fowles of Heaven muſt be filled with it, that is, the Devills and hell, for thither goe alive the <hi>Beast</hi> and the <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> ver. 20. and hell-fire de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth them, and becauſe we meet them ſo coupled in their finall &amp; fatall ruine, let us ſee their combination in all their Warres, and the expreſſion is thus. The <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his <hi>Image,</hi> the <hi>Beast</hi> and the <hi>falſe Prophet.</hi> The Beaſts Prophets are the Biſhops, and he is deceived with their hornes, that is, with the keyes, and by them they mould Kings into what Image they pleaſe, and therefore (good Reader) <hi>toties quoties,</hi> as often as thou meets them thus matched, make this their myſtery. The <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his <hi>Image,</hi> by Beaſt underſtand the falſe Prophet, or the Biſhop with two hornes, and by his Image, all Kings and Kingdomes moulded by him,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156202:5"/>
and then with eaſe thou wilt underſtand, that when Beaſt and falſe Prophet come together, the Beaſt muſt be Kings, and the falſe Prophets the Biſhops that deceive them, which is no more diſhonour to good Biſhops, then the falſe Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> were to the Prophets of the Lord. <hi>Where are thy Prophets,</hi> Jer. 37.19. that is, thy deceivers, <hi>O Zedekiah;</hi> have not I told thee the truth, that the <hi>Caldeans</hi> would come againe, and though <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of <hi>Egypt</hi> had wounded them all, yet ſhould they riſe up in their Tents, and borne the Citie, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>Where are the men of thy peace?</hi> Jer. 38.22. Thy Prophets that promiſed thee, that the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhould not returne, have deceived by their counſell, and prevailed, and faſtned thee in the myre, &amp;c. <hi>Pedes tui defixi funt in luto, retro converſi,</hi> from my counſell thou art gone, and invincibly tyed by flatterers in the mudde of thy own miſchiefe. Be wiſe therefore, yee Kings, how you fight for Antichriſt by the Lambes owne hornes, or your owne; let not the Biſhops be your Counſellours, as <hi>Auſten</hi> was when he came from <hi>Rome,</hi> but let ſuch as come from the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, with the right uſe of the keyes, command your Conſciences, (not your Crownes) to uſe them for the Lambe, and by his example to make warre; and give me leave firſt to begin with <hi>Piè regnare,</hi> to rule religiouſly, that is, from God as the cauſe, for God as the end, and by men as the meanes.</p>
            <p>And becauſe his Majeſtie ſaies the perſonall right is in him, as of any other thing he enjoyes, I will ſhew him plainly by Gods Word his errour, as the Parliament hath done by the Laws, confeſſing my ſelf a Royaliſt for his crown to be from God, and a friend of the kingdome to hold their own by Law which they have from God as well as his Majeſtie means to maintain what God hath given him. Come we to the iſſue between <hi>David</hi> and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> for the kingdome and his wife. They reſtore her without conditions, as being abſolutely <hi>Davids,</hi> and injuriouſly both taken from him by <hi>Saul,</hi> and kept from him by <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and therefore well might <hi>David</hi> ſay, <hi>See not my face,</hi> except my right in her be reſtored to me. Wife, children, goods belong to a King by commutative juſtice, and in them all, he hath a perſonall right, and is injured in the detaining of them from him by any force, or fraud. By this right he may not claime his kingdome, and ſay to his people <hi>the land is mine</hi> in commutative juſtice, for ſo it is not his but theirs: yet in diſtributive juſtice it is his not theirs, for God hath diſtributed to him the honour of the kingdome, but not the goods. Every man by Law is the owner of what is his, and all being put together the kingdome may keep from the King whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it hath, if by common conſent it will not grant it him. The Hiſtorian ſaies, <hi>Imperium iiſdem modis tenetur, quibus paratur,</hi> a kingdome is kept as it is gotten, and that is but two wayes, by <hi>conqueſt</hi> or by <hi>contract.</hi> The right of conqueſt, or rather the wrong, is obtained by the Sword and is ſo held, except people can by the ſame come to their right again. <hi>The Lord was with Hezekiah, and he proſpered whitherſoever he went forth: and he rebelled againſt the King of Aſſyria, and ſerved him not,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 18.7. The King is here in the caſe of his Subjects conquered by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156202:6"/>
the ſword, and the Rebellion is warranted by the Sword to recover what is loſt by it, and therefore Gods people need not to fear the title of the Sword, but cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly defend themſelves againſt it, which conquerours may call rebellion, but it is ſuch a rebellion as ſhall be proſpered by God, and therefore let Kings be wiſe that hold their kingdoms by contract, and keep it as God hath given it unto them. The foure Monarchies are ſo many tyrannies, becauſe they are both kept and come by in the tempeſts, and tumults of warre, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.2.3. <hi>Winds,</hi> that is, warres ſtrive, and Beaſts, not men, appear as they can get out of the Sea when they ſeek their greatneſſe.</p>
            <p>Come we to the ſecond, <hi>Rectè judicare,</hi> the Lambe makes warre in judgement, <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.11. and his word counſels all kings, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.18. <hi>With good advice make warre.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>unicum rectum conſilium, magnam mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litum manum vincit, Eurip.</hi> It is ſaid of <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> 1. Chron. 12.32. that the children of his Tribe were underſtanding men of the times to know what Iſrael ought to do. Its to be noted that all the Tribes that came to <hi>Hebron</hi> to ſerve <hi>David</hi> are ſet down by their ſeverall excellencies, and this Tribe is deſcribed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. by ſtrength, compared to the bone of an Aſſe able to bear any burden, and it is the beſt ſo to do, when prudence with patience makes us content to reſt quietly in a kingdome, and what we can to follow that judgement, that is the ſtay of all good government, and ſo he that is the <hi>King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> is a meek and patient Lambe, and ſtands firſt as an Angel at the Altar to receive petitions, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.3. as alſo he ſtands by it when it is meaſured, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11 1. as the Judge of truth, and he that is <hi>Agnus occiſus,</hi> a Lambe killed once for our ſinnes, is likewiſe <hi>Leo occidens,</hi> a killing Lion to all his Enemies; but before he kill in fight, he is found in judgement, and ſo ſhould all kings be. Its true, <hi>Armorum officia niſi juſſu principis ſint interdicta:</hi> that is, to private men, for God hath onely given the ſword to the Magiſtrate, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. who is not the Maſter of Arms, but the Miniſter of God, and is to revenge for him. Men of warre are the honour of the King, and the help of the Kingdom. It is in him by diſtributive juſtice to give the honour: but becauſe they help at the charge of the kingdom, juſtice commutative calls for the Councell thereof, and without common conſent no warre can be made. God had commanded his people to root out <hi>Amaleke</hi> from under heaven, and had laid his anathema or curſe upon the <hi>ſeven Nations,</hi> and ſo for warre with them no counſell was neceſſarie, but they might at all times fight againſt them, and becauſe when they overcame, they made them but Tributaries, <hi>Judg.</hi> 1.28. they were overcome and made Tributaries themſelves, and met with <hi>iron chariots, ver.</hi> 19. they could not conquer, and the ſtrong hold of <hi>Sion</hi> that the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> maintained to the dayes of <hi>David,</hi> and yet God was with them, but becauſe they were not wholly with him, he ſuffered them ſo often to fall into their hands that hated them, and yet helped them by <hi>Judges</hi> which for the moſt part were good, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured for faith, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.32. when the kings they deſired were few of them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156202:6"/>
good; for we are deceived in our thoughts of <hi>Monarchie,</hi> and do not diſtinguiſh it from an apparent <hi>Thearchie</hi> or divine Dynaſtie, wherein not the will of men, but of God is followed, and the people are happy that are at the will of one man, when his will is ruled by the will of God: but when kings follow their owne judgement their government is never good. There is one excellent reaſon why the <hi>Canaanites</hi> dwelt amongſt them, <hi>Judg.</hi> 3.1, 2. to learn them warre not as a bleſſing, for no warre is good in it ſelf, but to be wiſe and prudent is of excellent uſe, and to be taught by enemies, valour is vertue prized by God. I muſt tell my Nation the <hi>iron chariots,</hi> and the <hi>ſtrong holds of the Jebuſites</hi> that oppoſe it is for the ſinnes thereof, and yet to try our manhood to expell them at the laſt. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded warre needs no counſell, but where God is ſilent, no <hi>Iſraelite</hi> might fight but by the advice of their great Senate, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8. and to this the King was referred, <hi>verſe</hi> 14. and by it to him warre was permitted, and therefore Chriſt is an example of judgement in warre, and for method to make my mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer more plain, I will ſpeak of a threefold judgement, <hi>Judicium legis, Regis &amp; Regni,</hi> the Law, King, and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The judgement of the Law is this, <hi>Id Rex attribuat legi, quod Lex attribuit ei,</hi> Let the King yeeld that to the Law, which the Law hath yeelded to him. His Crowne, his Councell, his Kingdome, the Church, and Lawes of both are in his cuſtodie. <hi>Rex leget in libro legis, &amp;c.</hi> Deut. 17.19. the copie of the Law muſt be in his keeping, and for his learning; Firſt, to live by it; ſecondly, not to lift up himſelfe above his brethren; thirdly, to beware of Apoſtaſie; fourthly, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long his life; laſtly, to leave his Kingdome to his children. The Kings Crowne is not ſo much his by any inherence in himſelfe, or inheritance from others, as adherence to the Law. It both ſets on and keeps on his Crowne. He that reades the ſeven Seales of five judgements, hath but two mercies interlaced. The Goſpel in the firſt Seale, and the Law in the third. Of the Goſpel the Embleme is <hi>White;</hi> of the Law <hi>Blacke,</hi> and both for expedition are well mounted, and well armed. The firſt with a <hi>Bow</hi> and <hi>Crowne,</hi> to give honour to the conqvered, for whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver obeyes the Goſpel is crowned with felicitie. Law is ſevere and appeares in <hi>blacke</hi> with <hi>Balances</hi> to meaſure out all things. The two Horſes that oppoſe theſe are <hi>red</hi> and <hi>pale,</hi> bloud and death, warre and woe, to teach us all the true cauſes of our miſery. <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.25. <hi>I will bring a ſword upon you, that ſhall avenge the quarrell of my Covenant.</hi> The Crowne is not ſafe that keeps not the Covenant of the Law and Goſpel with Chriſt. Idolatry conſented unto by Chriſtian Kings, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion not regarded by them, hath deprived them of their Crownes, and cauſed ſo many alterations in all States.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, no King is above his Councell, but in it as a member. <hi>In ſolio Rex eſt ſine pars,</hi> In the royall ſeate the King hath no Peeres, but in <hi>Concilio habet pares,</hi> but in his Councell he hath Peeres, not to command him, but to agree with him, <hi>Conſilio, conſenſu, &amp; votis.</hi> Wee may reſolve two doubts: The firſt of a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156202:7"/>
vote; the ſecond of the Kings Supremacie. That the King hath a nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive vote, <hi>quoad intereſſe ſuum,</hi> no man can denie it, and the Lords and Commons have as much, and the reaſon is good, no one part can be injurious to another; but <hi>quoad intereſſe regni,</hi> of the common good of all the members, they are all bound to conſent to what is good, and to diſſent from what is evill. The privie Councell, Judges of the Land, Men of Warre, Officers of State, &amp;c. muſt all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their honours from the King. <hi>What ſhall be done to the man whom the King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth to honour?</hi> Eſther 6.6. Royall favours muſt come from his Majeſtie, but not with the hurt of the Subject. <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> reading the Chronicles of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and finding <hi>Mordecai</hi> to have done him good ſervice; will have him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, and <hi>Haman</hi> that had prepared the Gallowes for him, muſt be the Herald of his enemies praiſe; and when <hi>Hamon</hi> is found unworthy of his honour for the hurt he had done his Subjects, the King commands him to be hanged for <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai.</hi> Here is right diſtributive juſtice, and it is onely the Kings to give: But to denie his Councell hearing in the hurts of his people is moſt unjuſt, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutative juſtice pleads the Parliaments providence to provide for all theſe, and no King can denie it, and the contention riſeth that the King may not give ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, which is true when they hurt his Subjects, and the Parliament may ſee he be puniſhed whoſoever hath ſuch honours, and if by that Councell they may be deprived of them, doubtleſſe to ſave labour, they may adviſe the King not to give them, except he meane greater hurt to his people, then honour to his favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites. In point of Supremacie, we may thus be reſolved. <hi>Rex eſt Major ſingulis,</hi> the King is greater then his Subjects, <hi>Minor univerſis,</hi> leſſe then his Kingdome, and his Councell that repreſents it. No King needs to feare his Supremacie, for he both hath it <hi>ſine pari,</hi> and <hi>cum paribus.</hi> The Kingdome is his, but not by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt but contract. The Church is his to nurſe it with the ſincere milke of the Word, but not with the poyſon of Popery. The Lawes are his to keepe them, but not command them at his will. The judgement of the King in the diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of rewards &amp; penalties is properly his, as the proviſion in the vacancie of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, for ſuch accidents as happen above Law, beſide the Law, or beyond the reach of it. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltra, ſupra, praeter legem,</hi> the Prerogative is as neceſſary, as Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are to provide where Law is defective: but <hi>contra legem terrae,</hi> or fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Lawes commonly and conſtantly received in this Kingdome, neither King nor Councell are warranted at all, for both are to build upon that foundation. Furthermore, the King hath no legiſlative power, <hi>contra ſtatuta regni.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having then found out the maine matter of the Kings Prerogative in <hi>praemiis &amp; paenis,</hi> wee will to his honours adde <hi>poteſtatem vitae &amp; necis,</hi> and inſtance in that Indictment of Felons, <hi>Contra coronam &amp; dignitatem regis, &amp;c.</hi> It is the Scripture phraſe, <hi>Vir es mortis,</hi> thou art worthy to dye, <hi>Non morieris,</hi> thou ſhalt not dye, is the Kings mercie, and yet here his Majeſtie is limited, and his pardon proves voyd when there comes in <hi>intereſſe viri,</hi> the right of any one man, much more <hi>intereſſe regni.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:156202:7"/>
            <p>Come wee then to the judgement of the Kingdome, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.25. where wee have the ſame word <hi>Miſhphat,</hi> but applied to a more univerſall ſubject, as the judgement of the Kingdome, and ſo it is in the great Councell, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8, 9.11. There is a judgement in that place inferiour both to the King and Councell, and therefore what is too hard for inferiour Courts comes to the ſupreame, and that muſt be heard and feared of all. The great Charter of this Kingdome granted by <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, hath in it theſe three fundamentall Lawes, that completely ſecure every free man in this Kingdome, yet now moſt groſſely troden downe by our Caviliers, and his Majeſtie ſhould thinke how they ecclipſe his Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in a violation of it and all good Lawes. There is <hi>jus perſonarum, nullus liber ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo capietur, impriſonetur,</hi> the Law is that no free perſon be arreſted, impriſoned, or compelled to doe or ſuffer any thing, further then may juſtly be required by Law, Secondly, <hi>Jus rerum, quae noſtra ſunt ſine noſtro conſenſu à nobis tolli non poſſunt, fine furto Latricinio.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Jus actionum, nulli juſtitiam negabimus, &amp;c.</hi> How are theſe Lawes obſerved in the Kings Army? What man can reſiſt violence done to his perſon? ſave his goods from rapine, theeverie and Latrocinie? What a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or ſuit of Law can he have with lawleſſe men?</p>
            <p>Our laſt Point taken from our Captaine, is <hi>juſtè pugnare,</hi> to make warre in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. This appeares in foure things, in his <hi>veſture</hi> which he puts on, in his <hi>thigh</hi> which gives him iſſue, in his <hi>name</hi> which gaines him glory, and the inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it both upon veſture and thigh, to perpetuate his honour and fame to the worlds end. He puts not on the veſture of bloud, he is <hi>Dominus in albis,</hi> he and his appeare not like bloudy Souldiers, but Saints in the pureſt white, which may be dipt in bloud by others, yet is it not their naturall dye. From his thigh ſpring forth millions of men to be ſaved, though he ſmite his enemies, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did <hi>hip and thigh with a great ſlaughter.</hi> His name in ſo doing is above all names, and Kings and Lords muſt come under it. The inſcription of this honour remaines to this day on his <hi>veſture</hi> and <hi>thigh,</hi> maugre the malice of Antichriſt and all his members, whoſe reigne is moſt wicked, judgement corrupt, and warre cruell. They that cannot abide to be ſervants to God, are willing to be the greateſt ſlaves to the Devill. <hi>Gideon</hi> knowing the beſt Government to be a <hi>Thearchie,</hi> would not make himſelfe a Monarch at the requeſt of the people, <hi>Judg.</hi> 8.23. neither he nor his ſhould alter the forme of the Kingdome. God for him and them ſhould rule over his owne Nation, all that he will requeſt of them are the golden eare-rings gotten from the <hi>Iſhmaelites,</hi> amounting to a thouſand ſeven hundred Shekles of Gold, which the people give, and what will they not give to make an Idoll? They give beſide them, Ornaments, Collars, and Purple rayment, that was on the Kings of <hi>Midian,</hi> and beſide theſe the chains alſo that were about the Camels neckes. A maſſe of coſtly materialls to make an <hi>Ephod</hi> for a Monument of their deliverance. <hi>David</hi> danced in one not ſo coſtly as this for it ſeemes to riſe as high as <hi>Aarons Ephod.</hi> But <hi>Gideons</hi> good intention for God proved ſuperſtition in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156202:8"/>
people, who went a whoring after it, as ſoone as he was dead, and what he made for God, that they ſpeedily dedicated to <hi>Baal.</hi> Ready they were to change their Government, and to take any man for God that did them good, though he were but the inſtrument, and God to ſhew how the beſt men may fall, gives them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in ſome things, to ſhew they are but men. Thus was it with the Biſhops of the Church, who by the keyes of the Lambe gained power with his people, and might command eares and eare-rings, hearts and hands to ſet up any monument to God, and time turned all humane inventions into groſſe Idolatrie, and the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry keyes of Biſhops prevailed with Princes to goe higher then their eares, even to the top of their heads, and take off their crownes and caſt them into the laps of Biſhops, which have ſo handled their keyes, that they are become hornes held as upon the head of the Lambe, but made to fight againſt him, and having gotten ſuch intereſt in the Kings of the earth, and their Crownes, worke them as hornes with theirs to wage warre with the Lambe, and he is blinde that ſees it not in that part of the Street of the great Citie that is in our Kingdome. <hi>Brute,</hi> a Romane, for killing of his Father was baniſhed into this Land 1108 yeares before Chriſt, the firſt King we reade of in our Nation, and ſome 58 yeares before Chriſt, <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar</hi> being twice beaten out of the feild, and having his ſword taken from him by a valiant Duke, and <hi>Labianus</hi> a Romane Tribune ſlaine by it, yet civill warres gave <hi>Caeſar</hi> the Conqueſt in the end, and when he loſt his Crownes in all his Monarchie, he had the ſame fortune with us, and <hi>Vortiger,</hi> a murtherer of his lawfull Prince to hold that Crowne craves ayde of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and <hi>Hengiſt</hi> for his good ſervice marries his Daughter, and brings in the <hi>Saxons</hi> ſo faſt, that as tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling ſtones they came upon us, and at the laſt over-bare us, and then in this divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion comes in the Monke, and finds hornes fitted for him, and ſo the ten and two in all Kingdomes agree to warre with the Lambe, and theſe miſerable ſlaves to Satan, hold up his Soveraigntie againſt Chriſt, and not like <hi>Gideon</hi> grant Chriſt his due, but as the people will have it, take all to themſelves.</p>
            <p>We ſee in our dayes juriſdiction without Empire to doe well in the <hi>Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys,</hi> and the States rule, and their Generall the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> warres for them and they proſper, and may be ſome thinke they ſhould doe better, if the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> were their Emperour and the States changed to be his ſervants. There is Empire with Juriſdiction, &amp; this is two-fold, <hi>merum</hi> and <hi>mixtum Imperium.</hi> Meere Empire is abſolute Monarchie, and that is divine or humane. Divine, when God alone rules, the <hi>Lord ſhall rule over you,</hi> Judg. 8.23. yet at this time was there an <hi>Ariſtocratie</hi> aſſiſting this <hi>Thearchie,</hi> for Elders left by <hi>Moſes,</hi> Numb. 11.17. and that out-lived <hi>Joſhua,</hi> Judg, 2.7. kept the people to God, and might have done without kings in all ages; for we are miſtaken to tye God to them as by a Law of nature to rule the world. The Apoſtle ſaies not be ſubject to kings, but to the <hi>higher powers,</hi> Rom. 13.1. and to confirm us in them all, ſaies, <hi>Th re is no power but of God:</hi> and therefore to reſiſt one power with another is as well damnation,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156202:8"/>
as to withſtand one alone; and therfore the forms of Government muſt be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as well as the men. In the <hi>Thearchie</hi> of God the Elders as well as the Judges were to be obeyed, and may be with the diſobedience of God, the people diſobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Elders, and for both were puniſhed. Judges ſucceſſively one by one are raiſed, and for the life of their judge they are ſaid to obey, and being dead the people preſently ſin again, and I may think if they had been conſtant the people would have been the worſe, for if God had not humbled them by oppreſſion, and ſo for a time made them ſenſible of their ſorrow, they would, as they were in the wilderneſſe, have kicked at their Commanders, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.15. And it appears ſo at the laſt, as the book of the Judges ends their ſtory for <hi>Thearchie,</hi> that when they had no kings, that is, no Judges, <hi>every man did that which was right in his own eyes.</hi> This is arbitrary Government, when no form is obſerved, and as his Majeſtie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth the Parliament thereof, I dare ſay if we forſake that Government, our go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment will be as the King ſaith, an arbitrary Government, for meer Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie is no other. The two Horns have long ſtrugled for it, and the Pope hath gotten it over all Biſhops, and what is his Government but an arbitrarie rule to rule all men, as if all men ſhould rule themſelves, and becauſe <hi>Ceſar</hi> kept Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt from this meer Empire to the thraldome of all the world: ſo Antichriſt having gotten it from <hi>Ceſar,</hi> cannot endure one king to reign in <hi>Italie,</hi> Dan. 7.24. till he have ſubdued them all. I told you of <hi>Martian</hi> a good Emperor in the Eaſt, and the ſtory of him is that the <hi>Gothes, Vandales, Hunnes,</hi> and <hi>Herules,</hi> gained from him the Weſt, which in the dayes of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> belonged to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and from them it was gained again by the valour of <hi>Beliſarius, Mundus</hi> and <hi>Narſes,</hi> and loſt again to the <hi>Lombards,</hi> and by Antichriſt aſſiſted, by the <hi>French</hi> they are expelled, and the <hi>French</hi> too, and the two Horns evidently the abſolute Lord of <hi>Rome,</hi> and hath uſed his horns ſo well, that he hath by one means or another tamed all the <hi>ten horns,</hi> and either by power or policie makes them ſerve him. Its true hatred is ſpoken of, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.16. and in point of Supremacie, Princes have ſince <hi>Luther</hi> looked to this two horned Beaſt, but their hatred as yet is not hot enough to eat the fleſh of the Whore that Antichriſt labours to cheriſh in all Countreys. I ſaid this Whore ends her ſtreet with us; for <hi>Brute</hi> a Romane, and <hi>Ceſar,</hi> Romes perpetuus Dictator have given us more then <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> our denomination to be in the Romane juriſdiction, and I ſee Hiſtorians this way carrie it no further then us, which makes me ſuſpect this our preſent time to agree with <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.7. The ſtreet that from Jeruſalem ſtretcheth to us receives our dead bodies, that is, the Church and kingdom which politically are taken for the two witneſſes, for bleſſed be God, in ſpite of all that Antichriſt, but Church and Kingdom do witneſſe againſt him, and he muſt do to us as he hath done in other parts of this ſtreet over-ſeas, bring us into ſtraits with them, and the time is when they and we ſhall be about to finiſh our teſtimonie, and then riſeth the laſt warre to lay us as lowe as the graves mouth, but not to be able to bury us, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156202:9"/>
the reaſon is the ſame that we have, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 13.21. The invaſion of the Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites make the Iſraelites caſt by the dead body, and fall to their Armes. It is thought our Biſhops the worſt of them intended again to bury us in the grave of Poperie, and would have done it ſolemnly in an honourable mixture of their ſweet ſpices and ointments; and if <hi>Scotland</hi> had liked well of their preparation, we had gone down together into the grave without redemption. But <hi>Scotland</hi> taſted the Myrrhe and Aloes to be too bitter to be born by them, and there is no Nation up to hinder the buriall, and <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> follow, and over-ſeas the watres preceded, and God hath ſo tempered them, that if the Papiſts were at peace amongſt themſelves, they would put hard but they would heave us into their grave again, and make their own peace by our buriall. They are glad they have ſuch an opportunitie to kill us, but their joy will not be long to hurt us with their horns. That the horns of Antichriſt are in it is more then manifeſt, and our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſo blinded that they ſee it not, and if his Majeſtie cannot through the thick miſt ſee it, God of his goodneſſe expell the clouds that hinder it. Admiration it is, to ſee Papiſts flock to the Church, take the oath of Supremacie by ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation from the Pope, for certain it is he loves meer Monarchie, and may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Kings ſo to do; for if his Majeſtie would come to mixt Monarchie, and conſider that his Parliament by the form of Government in this Kingdom muſt joyn with him, he would not forſake it, or ſuffer Papiſts to abuſe his Crowns, to be as horns to goare his own body to prevent an arbitrarie Government where it cannot be, to ſet up one where it ought not to be. I ſay it is impoſſible to make the Parliament an Arbitrarie Government, for all the world cannot invent a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter means againſt it, and his Majeſtie ſaies the power of it is ſufficient to prevent tyrannie, and therefore it cannot ſet it up: But Anarchie, and abſolute Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie that is not Thearchie, is and ever will be an arbitrary form of Government, the good God of heaven preſerve us from both for we are in the way to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
